A Finding Aid to the Alexander Calder Papers, 1926-1967, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Alexander Calder papers
1926-1967
Archives of American Art
Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976
AAA.caldalex
Archival Resource Key
2.6 Linear feet
The papers of abstract kinetic artist and sculptor Alexander Calder measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1926 to 1967. Found within the papers are scattered biographical materials, correspondence, printed materials, photographs, scattered prints and sketches by Calder, and a scrapbook. Of particular interest are the numerous photographs of Calder, including many of Calder at work in his studios, with his family at their home in Touraine, France, exhibitions, and artwork. Among the photographs are several taken by photographer and artist Herbert Matter and a photograph of Pierre Matisse at Calder's home.
Biographical Note
Sculptor and kinetic artist Alexander Calder was born in 1898 in Lawnton, Pennsylvania. As the son of two artists, he was encouraged to sculpt and construct things in his own workshop at an early age. In 1919 he graduated from Stevens Institute of Technology with a degree in mechanical engineering, and after holding several jobs, he decided to take classes at the Art Students League in New York City. He began exhibiting his paintings, but also focused on drawing, illustration, and wood and wire sculpture. In 1926 Calder moved to Paris and began making toys for his performance piece, "Cirque Calder." He married Louisa James in 1931 and exhibited his mobiles for the first time the same year. He continued to spend his time between New York and Paris, and he and Louisa also bought a farm in Roxbury, Connecticut. They had two children, Sandra and Mary. Calder befriended many influential artists, including Joan Mirò, Fernand Léger, Marcel Duchamp, and Yves Tanguy, and joined the Abstraction-Création group in 1931. He exhibited and worked on commissions extensively throughout his career. As a very prolific artist, he had alliances with several galleries, including the Pierre Matisse Gallery in New York. Later in his career, Calder began focusing on large-scale outdoor sculptures. He died in 1976 at the age of 78.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of abstract kinetic artist and sculptor Alexander Calder measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1926 to 1967. Found within the papers are scattered biographical materials, correspondence, printed materials, photographs, scattered prints and sketches by Calder, and a scrapbook. Of particular interest are the numerous photographs of Calder, including many of Calder at work in his studios, with his family at their home in Touraine, France, exhibitions, and artwork. Among the photographs are several taken by photographer and artist Herbert Matter and a photograph of Pierre Matisse at Calder's home.
Biographical material contains a few of Calder's personal documents, including a passport and address lists, as well as writings. Correspondence is scattered and of a general nature, including letters about exhibitions and artwork, and postcards from friends, some of which are illustrated. The printed material contains exhibition invitations and catalogs, news clippings, and magazines, primarily about Calder's career. Also found is scattered artwork by Calder and others, and a scrapbook of news clippings dating from 1926-1932.
Arrangement
The Alexander Calder papers are arranged into six series, according to type of material. The contents of each folder have been arranged chronologically.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1928-1954, undated(Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1928-1962, undated (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1927-1967, undated(Box 1-3; 1 linear foot)
Series 4: Photographs, 1927-1962, undated (Box 3-6; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, 1930-1947, undated(Box 5-6; 1 folder)
Series 6: Scrapbook, 1926-1932 (Box 7; 1 item)
Provenance
The collection was donated in 1963 by Alexander Calder and was microfilmed shortly after receipt.
Related Material
The Archives also has a transcribed interview of Alexander Calder, conducted October 26, 1971 by Paul Cummings for the Archives of American Art.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Alexander Calder were digitized in 2005 by the Archives of American Art, and total 1086 images.
Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century; Sketches; Photographs; Sculptors; Sculpture, American; Scrapbooks
- Biographical Material, 1928-1954, undated; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 8 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical Material includes various address lists and business cards kept by Calder, his passport, notes, a catalog with handwritten prices, and other writings. Also found are a French tax document and other ephemera.
  - Address Lists, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annotated Catalog with Prices, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Business Cards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera, 1929-1943, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    (Partially scanned)
  - Notes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tax Document, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Passport, 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writings by Calder and Others, 1954, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1928-1962, undated; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 3 Folders Box 1
  This series includes correspondence to and from Calder. Much of the material is about exhibitions and works of art; also found are several postcards from friends. The series contains illustrated envelopes from Calder's son-in-law, Jean Davidson. Some items are in French.
  - Correspondence, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Illustrated Envelopes from Jean Davidson, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Printed Material, 1927-1967, undated; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 1-3
  Included in this series are invitations and catalogs for Calder exhibitions, including some international and rare items, news clippings about Calder, the bulk of which span from 1953 to 1955, and other miscellaneous news clippings compiled by Calder. Also found are various magazines and a publication on graphic arts.
  - Exhibition Invitations and Catalogs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Invitations and Catalogs, 1929-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Invitations and Catalogs, 1932-1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Invitations and Catalogs, 1935-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Invitations and Catalogs, 1952-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, Calder, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1927-1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1931-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1935-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, Calder, 1955-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, Miscellaneous, 1929-1954, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, Miscellaneous, 1929-1954, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Magazines, Miscellaneous, 1953-1956, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Portfolio: The Annual of Graphic Arts, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Photographs, 1927-1962, undated; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 3-6
  This series contains photographs of Calder, including formal portraits, Calder working in his studio, and spending time with his family. Among the photographs are several taken by photographer and artist Herbert Matter. Also found are numerous photographs of Calder at work on an unidentified mobile sculpture from 1954. This series also includes photographs of Calder's Home in Touraine, France, his studio, exhibitions, and his artwork.
  - Portraits of Calder, circa 1927- circa 1960, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Scope and Contents
    Oversized material housed in Box 6
  - Calder at Work, 1927-1956, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Calder at Work, 1927-1956, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Calder at Work on Mobile, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Calder at Work on Mobile (Duplicates), 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Calder's Home at Touraine, France, circa 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Calder with Family and Friends, 1932-1962, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Calder with Family and Friends, 1932-1962, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Calder with Family and Friends, 1932-1962, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Calder's Studio, 1939-1946, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Pierre Matisse at Calder's Home in France, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Exhibitions, 1953-1959, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1929-1958, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Oversize Photographs, Portraits of Calder, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 3, Folder 10
  - Oversize Photographs, Calder at Work, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 4, Folder 2
  - Oversize Photographs, Calder with Family and Friends, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 4, Folder 8
  - Oversize Photographs, Calder's Studio, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 4, Folder 9
  - Oversize Photographs, Artwork, Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 4
- Artwork, 1930-1947, undated; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Boxes 5-6
  Artwork includes lino cut prints sent to Calder from his nephew, Kenneth Hayes, as well as prints and sketches by Calder. Also found are three Japanese prints by an unidentified artist.
  - Artwork, 1930-1947, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Artwork, 1930-1947, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6)
    Oversized material digitized with Box 5, Folder 5
- Scrapbook, 1926-1932; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 7
  This series includes one scrapbook, originally a Chinese ledger notebook, containing newspaper clippings about Calder dating from 1926-1932, although it is marked "1929".
  - Scrapbook, 1926-1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)